<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<ead>
  <eadheader>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>Finding aid for the [Map of] Mackinac Island, Shewing [sic] the Surveys of Private Claims [electronic resource]</titleproper>
      </titlestmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Encoded finding aid created from MARC record by Dallas Pillen</creation>
      <langusage>The finding aid is written in <language langcode="eng">English</language></langusage>
      <descrules>appm</descrules>
    </profiledesc>
  </eadheader>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <did>
      <unitid>2014040 Aa 3</unitid>
      <origination>
        <persname encodinganalog="100" source="local">
          <primary_name>Mullett</primary_name>
          <rest_of_name>John</rest_of_name>
          <dates>1786-1862</dates>
        </persname>
      </origination>
      <unittitle>[Map of] Mackinac Island, Shewing [sic] the Surveys of Private Claims [electronic resource]</unittitle>
      <unitdate type="inclusive" label="creation">1828</unitdate>
      <physdesc>
        <extent>1 Ov. folder</extent>
        <physfacet>
ill.</physfacet>
      </physdesc>
    </did>
    <descgrp>
      <originalsloc>Original:
Clarke Historical Library, Central Michigan University, Mount Pleasant, Michigan.</originalsloc>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist>J. Mullett must be John Mullett, 1786-1862, a surveyor of many counties, cities, and areas in Mich. George Trustcott, born 1824 in Devon, England, married Sophia Bates, and eventually owned a green house and store on Mackinac Island. (Truscott information from ancestry.com, viewed Oct. 29, 2013.)</bioghist>
    <scopecontent>Hand drawn, paper survey map of Mackinac Island showing surveys, land patents, 1828 by J. Mullett, 1828. Scale 10 chains to 1 inch. The map identifies Military Reserve, Arch Rock, Robertson's Folly Rock, Mission House, Fort, Little Rock, and what are now the downtown areas. In the upper right is a list of lot and land patent numbers and 15 names of owners with the number of acres each owns. Note in pencil: 1 chain=66 feet; Note in pink ink: The rod numbers refer to the confirmation by the old Board of Commissioners. The map is signed on lower left by George Truscott. The map measures 21 x 22 inches. It is missing the upper right corner. The map suffers from cracks, tears, foxing, and acid stains, mostly from scotch tape on the back. On the back in pencil is the notation, Old Map Mackinac.</scopecontent>
    <controlaccess>
      <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="651">
        <term type="geographic">Mackinac Island (Mich. : Island)</term>
        <term type="topical">History.</term>
      </subject>
      <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="651">
        <term type="geographic">Mackinac Island (Mich. : Island)</term>
        <term type="genre_form">Maps.</term>
      </subject>
      <persname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="600">
        <primary_name>Mullett</primary_name>
        <rest_of_name>John</rest_of_name>
        <dates>1786-1862</dates>
      </persname>
      <persname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="600">
        <primary_name>Trustcott</primary_name>
        <rest_of_name>George</rest_of_name>
        <dates>1824-</dates>
      </persname>
    </controlaccess>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
