<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<ead>
  <eadheader>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>Finding aid for the Travelers Aid Society of Metropolitan Detroit records</titleproper>
      </titlestmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Encoded finding aid created from MARC record by Dallas Pillen</creation>
      <langusage>The finding aid is written in <language langcode="eng">English</language></langusage>
      <descrules>appm</descrules>
    </profiledesc>
  </eadheader>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <did>
      <unitid>04123 Bm 2</unitid>
      <origination>
        <corpname encodinganalog="110">
          <primary_name>Travelers Aid Society of Metropolitan Detroit</primary_name>
        </corpname>
      </origination>
      <unittitle>Travelers Aid Society of Metropolitan Detroit records</unittitle>
      <unitdate type="inclusive" label="creation">1929-1999</unitdate>
      <unitdate type="bulk" label="creation">(bulk 1950-1985)</unitdate>
      <physdesc>
        <extent>0.3 linear ft</extent>
      </physdesc>
    </did>
    <descgrp>
      <odd>
        <head>General Note</head>
        <p>Donor: 9514</p>
      </odd>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist>The Travelers Aid Society of Metropolitan Detroit was established in 1907, as part of St. John's Episcopal Church, with an emphasis on helping young women who arrived in the city alone. Services expanded, and in 1923 the Society became an independent organization, no longer associated with the church. The Society is now a member of the National Travelers Aid Association and focuses on helping many groups of people, including women, immigrants, individuals in the military, and other travelers with special needs. Their services include providing information on obtaining food and shelter for stranded and homeless individuals, orienting new arrivals to the services and rules of the city, and counseling runaway children.</bioghist>
    <scopecontent>Brochures, newspaper clippings, histories, and official documents of the Society, including the charter, constitution, and a few reports to directors; also videotapes (3) of public affairs programs featuring the Travelers Aid Society.</scopecontent>
    <controlaccess>
      <subject source="aat" encodinganalog="655">
        <term type="genre_form">Videotapes.</term>
      </subject>
      <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650">
        <term type="topical">Travelers' aid societies</term>
        <term type="geographic">Michigan</term>
        <term type="geographic">Detroit.</term>
      </subject>
      <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="651">
        <term type="geographic">Detroit (Mich.)</term>
      </subject>
      <corpname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="610">
        <primary_name>Travelers Aid Society of Metropolitan Detroit</primary_name>
      </corpname>
    </controlaccess>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
