<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<ead>
  <eadheader>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt><titleproper>Finding aid for the Picturesque Palestine, Sinai, and Egypt / ed. by Colonel Wilson ... assisted by the most eminent Palestine explorers, etc. With numerous engravings on steel and wood from original drawings by Harry Fenn and J. D. Woodward.</titleproper></titlestmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc><creation>Encoded finding aid created from MARC record by Dallas Pillen</creation><langusage>The finding aid is written in <language langcode="eng">English</language></langusage></profiledesc>
  <classification ref="/repositories/2/classifications/1"/></eadheader>
  <archdesc level="collection"><did><unitid>2012150 Aa 2</unitid><origination><persname encodinganalog="100" source="local"><primary_name>Wilson</primary_name><rest_of_name>Charles William</rest_of_name><title>Sir</title><dates>1836-1905</dates></persname></origination><unittitle>Picturesque Palestine, Sinai, and Egypt / ed. by Colonel Wilson ... assisted by the most eminent Palestine explorers, etc. With numerous engravings on steel and wood from original drawings by Harry Fenn and J. D. Woodward.</unittitle><unitdate type="inclusive" label="creation">[1881-81]</unitdate><physdesc><extent>2 v.</extent><physfacet>
ill., maps, plates</physfacet><dimensions>33 cm.</dimensions></physdesc></did><descgrp><odd><head>General Note</head><p>BHL: Bentley Historical Library's copy from the library of Rev. Henry Horatio Northrop.</p></odd><odd><head>Publication, Distribution, Etc.</head><p>New York : D. Appleton and Co., [1881-81]</p></odd><odd><head>Formatted Contents Note</head><p>v. 1. Introduction. By the Very Rev. Dean Stanley.--Jerusalem. By Col. Wilson.--Bethlehem and the north of Judea. By the Rev. Canon Tristram.--The mountains of Judah and Ephraim. By Lieut. Conder.--Samaria and Plain of Esdraelon. by Miss M.E. Rogers.--Esdraelon and Nazareth. by the Rev. Canon Tristram.--Galilee. Northern Galilee. Cæsarea Philippi and the highlands of Galilee. Mount Hermon and its temples. By the Rev. Dr. S. Merrill.--Demascus. By the Rev. Dr. P. Schaff.--Palmyra. The Wady Barada. Baʼalbek. By the Rev. S. Jessup. v. 2. Phœnicia and Lebanon. By the Rev. H.W. [!] Jessup.--The Phœnician plain. By the Rev. Canon Tristram.--Acre, the key of Palestine. Mount Carmel and the river Kishon. Maritime cities and plains of Palestine. by Miss M.E. Rogers.--Lydda and Ramlech. Philistia. by Lt. col. Warren.--The south country of Judæa. By the Rev. Canon Tritram.--The southern borderland and Dead sea. By Professor Palmer.--Mount Hor and the cliffs of Edom. The convent of St. Catherine. By Miss M.E. Rogers.--Sinai, by the Rev. C.P. Clarke.--The land of Goshen. Cairo. Memphis. Thebes. Edfû and Philæ. By S. Lane-Poole.</p></odd><odd><head>General Note</head><p>Added t.-p., engraved: Issued in 40 parts.</p></odd></descgrp><controlaccess><subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="651"><term type="geographic">Palestine</term><term type="topical">Description and travel.</term></subject><subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="651"><term type="geographic">Sinai (Egypt)</term><term type="topical">Description and travel.</term></subject></controlaccess><container label="Volume" type="volume">1</container><container label="Volume" type="volume">2</container></archdesc>
</ead>
