<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<ead>
  <eadheader>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>Finding aid for the Ruth Marie Barnes collection</titleproper>
      </titlestmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Encoded finding aid created from MARC record by Dallas Pillen</creation>
      <langusage>The finding aid is written in <language langcode="eng">English</language></langusage>
      <descrules>dacs</descrules>
    </profiledesc>
    <classification ref="/repositories/2/classifications/1"/>
  </eadheader>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <did>
      <unitid>2014045 Aa 2</unitid>
      <origination>
        <persname role="col" encodinganalog="100" source="local">
          <primary_name>Barnes</primary_name>
          <rest_of_name>Ruth Marie</rest_of_name>
          <dates>1899-1997</dates>
        </persname>
      </origination>
      <unittitle>Ruth Marie Barnes collection</unittitle>
      <physdesc altrender="whole">
        <extent altrender="materialtype spaceoccupied">0.2 linear feet</extent>
      </physdesc>
      <langmaterial>In English.</langmaterial>
      <unitdate type="inclusive" label="creation">1918-1919 and undated</unitdate>
    </did>
    <descgrp>
      <accruals>No further accruals are expected.</accruals>
      <accessrestrict>The collection is open for research use.</accessrestrict>
      <acqinfo>Donor: 8206</acqinfo>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist>Ruth Marie Barnes was born in Dowagiac, Michigan on April 19, 1899. She graduated from Battle Creek High School in 1917 and from Michigan State Normal School in 1919, having lived with her aunt and uncle James Galbraith, at 821 Oakland in Ann Arbor, Mich. during her college years. She moved to Lansing, Mich. to teach 2nd graders at Warner (now Willow) Street School, married Freeman H. McClintock in 1926, had two children, Mary Jane and William James. She was active in many community groups and was a longtime member of St. Paul's Episcopal Church. She died January 3, 1997 in Lansing, Mich.</bioghist>
    <scopecontent>Collected University of Michigan materials include programs of the Glee and Mandolin Club, Michigan Union Opera, School of Music faculty, and the Choral Union series performances; and programs of meetings of various clubs and societies. Also included two similar items from the Ann Arbor High School and Michigan State Normal School. Collection includes Michigan State Normal School handwritten teaching program and class papers: "Commandments for Teachers" and lesson plans for various subjects. Also a Crest restaurant menu.</scopecontent>
    <controlaccess>
      <corpname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="610">
        <primary_name>Michigan State Normal School</primary_name>
      </corpname>
      <corpname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="610">
        <primary_name>University of Michigan</primary_name>
        <term type="topical">Students</term>
        <term type="topical">Social life and customs</term>
        <term type="temporal">1911-1920.</term>
      </corpname>
    </controlaccess>
    <container label="Box" type="box">1</container>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
