<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<ead>
  <eadheader>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper>Finding aid for the Freedom of Information Office (University of Michigan) records</titleproper>
      </titlestmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Encoded finding aid created from MARC record by Dallas Pillen</creation>
      <langusage>The finding aid is written in <language langcode="eng">English</language></langusage>
      <descrules>dacs</descrules>
    </profiledesc>
  </eadheader>
  <archdesc level="collection">
    <did>
      <unitid>2015050 Bimu 2</unitid>
      <origination>
        <corpname encodinganalog="110">
          <primary_name>University of Michigan</primary_name>
          <subordinate_name>Freedom of Information Office</subordinate_name>
        </corpname>
      </origination>
      <unittitle>Freedom of Information Office (University of Michigan) records</unittitle>
      <langmaterial>In English.</langmaterial>
      <unitdate type="inclusive" label="creation">1995-2004</unitdate>
      <unitdate type="bulk" label="creation">bulk 1995-1998</unitdate>
      <physdesc>
        <extent>1 linear foot</extent>
      </physdesc>
    </did>
    <descgrp>
      <accessrestrict>Restricted access. Contact the repository.</accessrestrict>
      <otherfindaid>Finding aid in the library.</otherfindaid>
      <odd>
        <head>General Note</head>
        <p>Donor: 9493</p>
      </odd>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist>The Freedom of Information Office responds to requests for information about the University of Michigan made through the Michigan Freedom of Information Act. In particular, this collection contains the set of requests that led to the Gratz v. Bollinger and Grutter v. Bollinger Supreme Court cases regarding affirmative action policies at the University of Michigan.</bioghist>
    <scopecontent>The collection contains requests from 1995 to 1998 regarding admissions and affirmative action at the University of Michigan. Those making requests included Carl Cohen, Richard Cutler, Maryanne George, Thomas Giles, Rusty Hoover, David Jaye, Heather Kamins, Douglas Lederman, Michelle McManus, David Murley, Gerald Reynolds, Brent Simmons, Zack Sharon, Art Stine. Each file contains the original letter of request and the letter of response with resulting documents.</scopecontent>
    <controlaccess>
      <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650">
        <term type="topical">Freedom of information</term>
        <term type="geographic">Michigan.</term>
      </subject>
      <corpname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="610">
        <primary_name>Michigan</primary_name>
        <term type="uniform_title">Freedom of Information act.</term>
      </corpname>
      <corpname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="610">
        <primary_name>University of Michigan</primary_name>
        <subordinate_name>Freedom of Information Office</subordinate_name>
      </corpname>
    </controlaccess>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
