<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE ead PUBLIC "+//ISBN 1-931666-00-8//DTD ead.dtd (Encoded Archival Description (EAD) Version 2002)//EN" "ead.dtd">
<ead>
  <eadheader audience="internal" langencoding="iso639-2b" repositoryencoding="iso15511" dateencoding="iso8601" relatedencoding="Dublin Core">
    <eadid countrycode="us" mainagencycode="MiU-H" publicid="us//::miu-h//TXT us::miu-h::kahnfam.xml//EN" encodinganalog="identifier">umich-bhl-0442</eadid>
    <filedesc>
      <titlestmt>
        <titleproper encodinganalog="title">Finding Aid for Albert Kahn Family Papers, 1869-2015</titleproper>
        <author encodinganalog="creator">Collection processed and finding aid created by Sally Linvill Bund, March 1, 2004, May 25, 2016.</author>
      </titlestmt>
      <publicationstmt>
        <publisher encodinganalog="publisher">Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan</publisher>
        <date encodinganalog="date">2004</date>
      </publicationstmt>
    </filedesc>
    <profiledesc>
      <creation>Encoded finding aid created by Greg Kinney <date>2004-06-04</date></creation>
      <langusage>The finding aid is written in <language langcode="eng">English</language></langusage>
    </profiledesc>
    <revisiondesc>
      <change>
        <date>2016-05-24</date>
        <item>Contents list re-encoded with new accessions.</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date>2009-11-11</date>
        <item>Changes made with the addition of new material.</item>
      </change>
      <change>
        <date>2004-06-04</date>
        <item>Original encoding from Word 6.0 file using Word macros and Xmetal.</item>
      </change>
    </revisiondesc>
  </eadheader>
  <frontmatter>
    <titlepage>
      <publisher>Michigan Historical Collections <lb/>Bentley Historical Library <lb/>University of Michigan</publisher>
      <titleproper>Finding aid for <lb/>Albert Kahn Family Papers, 1869-2015</titleproper>
      <author>Finding aid created by <lb/>Sally Linvill Bund, March 1, 2004, Nay 25, 2016</author>
    </titlepage>
  </frontmatter>
  <archdesc level="collection" audience="external" type="inventory" relatedencoding="MARC21">
    <did>
      <origination>
        <famname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="100">Kahn family.</famname>
      </origination>
      <unittitle encodinganalog="245">Albert Kahn Family papers <unitdate type="inclusive" encodinganalog="245$f" normal="1869/1989">1869-1989</unitdate></unittitle>
      <unitid encodinganalog="099" repositorycode="MiU-H" countrycode="us" type="call number">0442 Aa/2</unitid>
      <langmaterial>The material is in <language langcode="eng" encodinganalog="041">English</language></langmaterial>
      <abstract>The Albert Kahn Family Papers include the personal correspondence of Albert, his wife Ernestine Krolik Kahn, his son Edgar Adolph Kahn, and his daughter Ruth Kahn Rothman, miscellaneous materials which document the personal and professional lives of family members, and photographic images from the 1870s to 2015.</abstract>
      <physdesc altrender="whole">
        <extent altrender="materialtype spaceoccupied">4 linear feet</extent>
      </physdesc>
      <repository>
        <corpname encodinganalog="852"><subarea>Bentley Historical Library</subarea>, University of Michigan</corpname>
        <extptr href="bhladd" show="embed" actuate="onload"/>
      </repository>
    </did>
    <descgrp type="admin">
      <acqinfo encodinganalog="541">
        <p>The collection came from Carol Kahn (Donor No. 9202) on 5/15/2002 and 12/3/2014; additional papers came from William R. Brashear (donor no. 9864) on 3/14/2007 and 7/10/2009, Ruth Brashear Carrigan (donor no. 11089) on 4/9/2014, 11/8/2014 and 5/15/2015, and Elizabeth Lehndorff (donor no. 11330) on 6/22/1015</p>
      </acqinfo>
      <acqinfo encodinganalog="541">
        <p>The collection came from Carol Kahn (Donor No. <num type="donor" encodinganalog="541$e">9202</num>) on 5/15/2002 and 12/3/2014; additional papers came from William R. Brashear (Donor No. <num type="donor" encodinganalog="541$e">9864</num>) on 3/14/2007 and 7/10 2009; Ruth Brashear Carrigan (donor no. <num type="donor" encodinganalog="541$e">11089</num>) on 4/9/2014, 11/8/2014 and 5/15/2015, and Elizabeth Lehndorff (donor no. <num type="donor" encodinganalog="541$e">113309</num>) on 6/22/1015.</p>
      </acqinfo>
      <accessrestrict encodinganalog="506">
        <p>The collection is open for research with the exception of two folders containing client information which are closed until July 1, 2035.</p>
      </accessrestrict>
      <userestrict encodinganalog="540">
        <p>Copyright has been transferred to the Regents of the University of Michigan.</p>
      </userestrict>
      <prefercite encodinganalog="524">
        <p>[item], folder, box, Albert Kahn Family Papers, Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan</p>
      </prefercite>
    </descgrp>
    <bioghist encodinganalog="545">
      <p>As America's most influential industrial architect, Albert Kahn revolutionized the health and safety conditions of early twentieth-century factories and worked closely with Henry Ford to implement his vision of the assembly line at the Highland Park and River Rouge automobile plants. Kahn pioneered the use of reinforced concrete, non-intrusive steel structures, natural ventilation and glass building skins to respond to the changing functional needs of the American factory. His pragmatism, ability to listen to the needs of the client and experimentation with innovative building technologies resulted in a new industrial architecture, which inspired the development of European Modernism by Walter Gropius, Mies van der Rohe and Le Corbusier. Hugely versatile in his design capabilities and strongly interested in historic architecture, Kahn also produced many commercial and institutional icons in Detroit and at the University of Michigan, including the Fisher Building, Detroit Athletic Club, General Motors Building, Hill Auditorium, Angell Hall, William L. Clements Library and Burton Memorial Carillon Tower. This most prolific of American architects built over 2000 projects in his lifetime, including 521 factories in Russia between 1929 and 1932, and in 1938 was constructing 19% of all architect-designed industrial facilities in the United States. When he died in 1942, he had signed defense contracts totaling $200 million for the construction of the Willow Run Bomber Plant and naval bases in Honolulu, Midway Island, Puerto Rico and Kodak, Alaska, among other war-time facilities.</p>
      <p>In 1896, Kahn married Ernestine Krolik, the daughter of Adolph Krolik, who was a successful dry goods merchant and a client of the young architect. A graduate of the University of Michigan in 1892, Ernestine was a talented gardener and interior designer, who often advised Albert on matters of color and fabric selection. When speaking of her parents, their daughter Rosalie Kahn Butzel said years later that "they complemented each other wonderfully."[1] Albert and Ernestine had two other daughters, Lydia and Ruth, and one son, Edgar (1900-1985). "Eddie" became the first scorer and captain of the University of Michigan hockey team, graduating from the University Medical School in 1924. From 1949 to 1971, he served as the Chairman of Neurosurgery at the University of Michigan Hospital (designed by his father in 1919).</p>
      <p>---------</p>
      <p>1) Richard Bak, "Blueprint for Detroit," HOUR Detroit (May, 2000, reprinted by Albert Kahn Associates, Inc.), p. 2.</p>
    </bioghist>
    <arrangement encodinganalog="351">
      <p> The Albert Kahn Family Papers are arranged in three series, named for the donors of the materials: Kahn Family Papers, Carol Kahn, collector; Kahn Family Papers, William R. Brashear and Ruth Brashear Carrigan, collectors; and Kahn Family Papers, Elizabeth (Betsy) Kahn Lehndorff, collector. </p>
    </arrangement>
    <scopecontent encodinganalog="520">
      <p>The Kahn Family Papers have come to the library from four sources: from Carol Kahn, the granddaughter of Albert and Ernestine Kahn and daughter of Edgar A. Kahn; from William R. Brashear, who was married to Albert's and Ernestine's granddaughter, Lydia Rothman Brashear; from William Brashear's daughter, Ruth Brashear Carrigan; and from Edgar Kahn's daughter, Elizabeth Kahn Lehndorff. The Albert Kahn Family Papers received from Carol Kahn include letters and photographs which contribute to our understanding of Kahn's relationship with his wife, children and grandchildren. The materials also illuminate the distinguished military and professional careers of his son Edgar (1900-1985), who served as Chairman of Neurosurgery at the University of Michigan Hospital from 1949 to 1971. The papers received from William R. Brashear and his daughter Ruth Carrigan document the personal and professional lives of Albert and Ernestine Kahn, Ruth Kahn Rothman, Edward E. Rothman and other members of the extended Kahn family, including Albert Kahn's granddaughters, Josephine Rothman Treutner and Lydia Rothman Brashear. Mr. Brashear's collection also encompasses family letters and photographs, which are contained in his book, <title render="italic">Albert Kahn and His Family in Peace and War</title>, published by the Bentley Historical Library in 2006. The materials donated by Elizabeth (Betsy) Lehndorff relate to her recent careers as a journalist in Colorado and as a jewelry artist in Alpena, Michigan.</p>
    </scopecontent>
    <controlaccess>
      <p>
        <extptr href="accnote" show="embed" actuate="onload"/>
      </p>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Subjects:</head>
        <famname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="600">Kahn family.</famname>
        <subject source="lcsh" encodinganalog="650">Architects--Michigan--Detroit.</subject>
        <persname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="600" authfilenumber="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n88163469">Kahn, Albert, 1869-1942.</persname>
        <persname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="600">Kahn, Edgar A.</persname>
        <persname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="600">Kahn, Ernestine Krolik.</persname>
        <persname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="600">Rothman, Ruth Kahn.</persname>
        <corpname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="610">University of Michigan. University Hospital.</corpname>
        <corpname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="610">University of Michigan. Dept. of Neurosurgery.</corpname>
      </controlaccess>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Subjects - Visual Materials:</head>
        <corpname encodinganalog="610" source="lcnaf" authfilenumber="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n2015183833">University of Michigan. Section of Neurosurgery.</corpname>
        <corpname encodinganalog="610" source="lcnaf" authfilenumber="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n79021846">University of Michigan--Hockey.</corpname>
        <persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcnaf">Kahn, Albert.</persname>
        <persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcnaf">Kahn, Edgar A.</persname>
        <persname encodinganalog="600" source="lcnaf">Kahn, Ernestine.</persname>
      </controlaccess>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Contributors</head>
        <persname source="lcnaf" encodinganalog="700" authfilenumber="http://id.loc.gov/authorities/names/n87101284">Peet, Max Minor.</persname>
      </controlaccess>
      <controlaccess>
        <head>Genre Terms:</head>
        <genreform encodinganalog="655" source="aat">Photographs.</genreform>
      </controlaccess>
    </controlaccess>
    <dsc type="combined">
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Kahn Family Papers, Carol Kahn, collector</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>The first series, Carol Kahn, collector, encompasses four sub-series, related to the lives of Albert and Ernestine Kahn, Mollie Kahn Fuchs, Edgar A. Kahn and Carol Kahn. Researchers will find a number of interesting early letters within the Albert and Ernestine Kahn Correspondence sub-series. While the letters from Albert number only four, his letter to his sister-in-law Amy of 11/9/1900 is of particular interest. In this hand-written piece of correspondence, Kahn recounts his delight in visiting Paris, Genoa, and Florence in 1891 and includes a sketch of an Italian arch. He also expresses pride and delight in his baby son, Edgar. Two late letters of 6/26/1940 and 7/17/1942 to Edgar, who was posted for military duty in Spain and Little Rock, Arkansas, are also significant. In these documents, Kahn describes his own war defense work and expresses concern for his son's welfare. He gives us a glimpse of paternal emotion when he ends the 1940 letter with these words to Eddie: "You mean everything to all of us." The four letters to Kahn in this sub-series include two from his brother Julius (one dated 1/14/1900), with whom he collaborated on the use of reinforced concrete in structural design. And a letter from his first partner Alexander Buel Trowbridge (10/17/1898), who had recently become the dean of the Cornell University College of Architecture, documents this early professional relationship.</p>
        </scopecontent>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Albert and Ernestine Kahn</unittitle>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>Within the Albert and Ernestine Correspondence sub-series, the letters written by Kahn's future wife Ernestine Krolik, at the age of 16, give researchers a view of the personality of this intelligent, young woman, who shows herself to be cultured, confident and family-oriented. Twenty-one letters were written by Ernestine during her summer visit in St. Paul, Minnesota, from 6/29/1885 to 9/1/1885. They were addressed to her mother, sister Bell, brother Day and father Adolph Krolik, a dry goods merchant who would later become a client of Albert Kahn. In addition to her descriptions of her train trips to such tourist destinations as Lake Johanna, White Bear Lake and Lake St. Croix, she provides detailed walking-tour portraits of the cities of St. Paul and Minneapolis in 1885. Her letters show her to have a game sense of adventure, as well as a strong devotion to her parents, whose "kindness and warm-heartedness" she praises. Included in the letters to Ernestine is a 1942 Western Union telegram from V. A. Vernin, a Russian architect-academician, expressing "sympathy in connection with the death of your husband Mr. Albert Kahn, who rendered us great service in designing a number of large plants and helped us to assimilate the American experience in the sphere of [the] building industry."</p>
          </scopecontent>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Correspondence</unittitle>
            </did>
            <c04 level="file">
              <did>
                <unittitle>Albert Kahn</unittitle>
              </did>
              <c05 level="file">
                <did>
                  <container type="box" label="Box">1</container>
                  <unittitle>From Albert, <unitdate type="inclusive">ca. 1896-1942</unitdate></unittitle>
                </did>
              </c05>
              <c05 level="file">
                <did>
                  <container type="box" label="Box">1</container>
                  <unittitle>To Albert, <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1898/1900">1898-1900</unitdate></unittitle>
                </did>
              </c05>
            </c04>
            <c04 level="file">
              <did>
                <unittitle>Ernestine Krolik Kahn</unittitle>
              </did>
              <c05 level="file">
                <did>
                  <container type="box" label="Box">1</container>
                  <unittitle>From Ernestine, <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1885/1943">1885-1943</unitdate></unittitle>
                </did>
              </c05>
              <c05 level="file">
                <did>
                  <container type="box" label="Box">1</container>
                  <unittitle>To Ernestine, <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1887/1942">1887-1942</unitdate></unittitle>
                </did>
              </c05>
            </c04>
            <c04 level="file">
              <did>
                <container type="box" label="Box">1</container>
                <unittitle>Miscellaneous, <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1881/1894">1881-1894</unitdate></unittitle>
              </did>
            </c04>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Miscellaneous Papers</unittitle>
            </did>
            <c04 level="file">
              <did>
                <container type="box" label="Box">1</container>
                <unittitle>Kahn Family Tree</unittitle>
              </did>
            </c04>
            <c04 level="file">
              <did>
                <container type="box" label="Box">1</container>
                <unittitle>Ernestine Kahn's school certificates, <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1880/1887">1880-1887</unitdate></unittitle>
              </did>
            </c04>
            <c04 level="file">
              <did>
                <container type="box" label="Box">1</container>
                <unittitle>Program for the Dedication of the William L. Clements Library of American History, <unitdate type="inclusive">6/15/1923</unitdate></unittitle>
              </did>
            </c04>
            <c04 level="file">
              <did>
                <container type="box" label="Box">1</container>
                <unittitle>Detroit Institute of Arts, Thumb Tack Club of Detroit, Architectural Exhibition Catalog, <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1928">1928</unitdate></unittitle>
              </did>
            </c04>
            <c04 level="file">
              <did>
                <container type="box" label="Box">1</container>
                <unittitle>Suggested design of Albert Kahn U. S. Postal Stamp, <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1971">1971</unitdate></unittitle>
              </did>
            </c04>
            <c04 level="file">
              <did>
                <container type="box" label="Box">1</container>
                <unittitle>Nomination of Albert Kahn Residence to National Register of Historic Places, <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1972">1972</unitdate></unittitle>
              </did>
            </c04>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Photographs</unittitle>
            </did>
            <c04 level="file">
              <did>
                <container type="box" label="Box">1</container>
                <unittitle>Ernestine and Joe Krolik, <unitdate type="inclusive">ca. 1870s</unitdate> </unittitle>
                <physdesc>
                  <extent>one 2-1/2x4-inch, black-and-white print</extent>
                </physdesc>
              </did>
            </c04>
            <c04 level="file">
              <did>
                <container type="box" label="Box">1</container>
                <unittitle>Ernestine Krolik with others, <unitdate type="inclusive">undated</unitdate> </unittitle>
                <physdesc>
                  <extent>one 1-1/2x3-1/2-inch, black-and-white print</extent>
                </physdesc>
              </did>
            </c04>
            <c04 level="file">
              <did>
                <container type="box" label="Box">1</container>
                <unittitle>Albert Kahn's parents, Joe and Rosalie, with 8 children, <unitdate type="inclusive">undated</unitdate> </unittitle>
                <physdesc>
                  <extent>one 9x11-inch, black-and-white print</extent>
                </physdesc>
              </did>
            </c04>
            <c04 level="file">
              <did>
                <container type="box" label="Box">1</container>
                <unittitle>Albert and Ernestine Kahn's children, <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1901/1908">1901-1908</unitdate> </unittitle>
                <physdesc>
                  <extent>five 2x3 to 4x5-1/2-inch, black-and-white prints</extent>
                </physdesc>
              </did>
            </c04>
            <c04 level="file">
              <did>
                <container type="box" label="Box">1</container>
                <unittitle>Albert and Ernestine Kahn's Walnut Lake cottage, <unitdate type="inclusive">undated</unitdate> </unittitle>
                <physdesc>
                  <extent>one 8x10-inch, black-and-white print</extent>
                </physdesc>
              </did>
            </c04>
            <c04 level="file">
              <did>
                <container type="box" label="Box">1</container>
                <unittitle>Albert and Ernestine Kahn, <unitdate type="inclusive">undated</unitdate> </unittitle>
                <physdesc>
                  <extent>two color prints, 5x7 and 2x3 inches</extent>
                </physdesc>
              </did>
            </c04>
            <c04 level="file">
              <did>
                <container type="box" label="Box">1</container>
                <unittitle>Albert Kahn with airplane, <unitdate type="inclusive">undated</unitdate> </unittitle>
                <physdesc>
                  <extent>one 3-1/2x5-inch, black-and-white print</extent>
                </physdesc>
              </did>
            </c04>
            <c04 level="file">
              <did>
                <container type="box" label="Box">1</container>
                <unittitle>Albert Kahn, <unitdate type="inclusive">11/3/1941</unitdate> </unittitle>
                <physdesc>
                  <extent>one 8x10-inch, black-and-white original and one copy print</extent>
                </physdesc>
              </did>
            </c04>
            <c04 level="file">
              <did>
                <container type="box" label="Box">1</container>
                <unittitle>Albert, Ernestine and Edgar Kahn, <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1942">1942</unitdate> </unittitle>
                <physdesc>
                  <extent>one 8x10-inch, black-and-white print</extent>
                </physdesc>
              </did>
            </c04>
            <c04 level="file">
              <did>
                <container type="box" label="Box">1</container>
                <unittitle>Ernestine Kahn with Edgar, Lydia, Ruth and Rosalie, <unitdate type="inclusive">undated</unitdate> </unittitle>
                <physdesc>
                  <extent>one 8x10-inch, black-and-white print</extent>
                </physdesc>
              </did>
            </c04>
            <c04 level="file">
              <did>
                <container type="box" label="Box">1</container>
                <unittitle>Ernestine Kahn, <unitdate type="inclusive">undated</unitdate> </unittitle>
                <physdesc>
                  <extent>one 9x11-inch, black-and-white print)</extent>
                </physdesc>
              </did>
            </c04>
            <c04 level="file">
              <did>
                <container type="box" label="Box">1</container>
                <unittitle>Unidentified Photos, <unitdate type="inclusive">undated</unitdate> </unittitle>
                <physdesc>
                  <extent>two black-and-white prints, 2-1/2x3 and 2-1/2x4-1/2 inches</extent>
                </physdesc>
              </did>
            </c04>
          </c03>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Mollie Kahn Fuchs</unittitle>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>The Mollie Fuchs Kahn sub-series contains her "Memoirs" (1937), a very important first-hand telling of the story of the Kahn children's first decades in America with parents, Joseph and Rosalie Kahn. Researchers seeking to understand the early years of Albert Kahn and the challenges of this hard-working immigrant family will find the "Memoirs" of great interest.</p>
          </scopecontent>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <container type="box" label="Box">1 </container>
              <unittitle>"Memoirs," <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1877/1937">1877-1937</unitdate></unittitle>
            </did>
          </c03>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Edgar Adolph Kahn</unittitle>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>The Edgar Adolph Kahn sub-series contains a large body of material related to the personal life and illustrious medical career of Albert's and Ernestine's only son (1900-1985). These documents, both textual and visual, offer a rich perspective on Edgar's childhood, World War II military experience, medical career as Chief of Neurosurgery at University of Michigan Hospital (1949-1971), family, travels and writings. As a whole, they flesh out a picture of his strengths as a leader and his relationships as a son, husband and father.</p>
            <p>Letters within the Edgar Kahn sub-series range from congratulatory notes to his parents at the time of his birth to his correspondence with his friends and colleagues, including his mentor Dr. Max M. Peet, in the Neurosurgery Department at the University of Michigan. The letters to Dr. Peet describe Edgar's further medical training in London in 1936 and his military service at Kennedy General Hospital in Memphis, Tennessee, as World War II came to an end. Peet's letters to Edgar in 1942 and 1945 give researchers a view of the changes and challenges at University Hospital during the war years. Letters from other physicians document Edgar Kahn's stature in the field of neurosurgery. Personal correspondence with his parents during World War II are also of interest.</p>
            <p>Edgar Kahn's illustrious neurosurgery career at the University of Michigan and in national organizations is well documented in this sub-series, with early notes on his practice (1926), transcription of his speeches and professional journal submissions. Newspaper articles about his medical career, his distinguished service during the war and even his hockey prowess, while a student at the University of Michigan in 1921, give additional perspective on his diverse achievements in medicine and other areas.</p>
            <p>The photographs in the Edgar Kahn sub-series pertain to his youth, his school years at Andover and the University of Michigan, his European travels, his military service and his medical career in the neurosurgical operating room. These often intimate glimpses of Edgar in various states of relaxation with colleagues, friends and his wife Rose are significant in providing researchers with a sense of the strong relationships in Edgar's life. The audio-visual materials in this sub-series range from an important reel-to-reel-taped interview, which his daughter Carol conducted with her father in 1978, to audio tapes of one of Edgar's professional speeches and of his memorial service in 1985.</p>
          </scopecontent>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Correspondence</unittitle>
            </did>
            <c04 level="file">
              <did>
                <container type="box" label="Box">1</container>
                <unittitle>Letters of congratulations to Albert and Ernestine Kahn regarding Edgar's birth, <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1900">1900</unitdate></unittitle>
              </did>
            </c04>
            <c04 level="file">
              <did>
                <container type="box" label="Box">1</container>
                <unittitle>To Edgar, <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1928/1985">1928-1985</unitdate></unittitle>
              </did>
            </c04>
            <c04 level="file">
              <did>
                <container type="box" label="Box">1</container>
                <unittitle>From Edgar, <unitdate type="inclusive">ca. 1924-1984</unitdate></unittitle>
              </did>
            </c04>
            <c04 level="file">
              <did>
                <container type="box" label="Box">1</container>
                <unittitle>To Albert and Ernestine Kahn about Edgar, <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1910/1940">1910-1940</unitdate></unittitle>
              </did>
            </c04>
            <c04 level="file">
              <did>
                <container type="box" label="Box">1</container>
                <unittitle>From Edgar to Ernestine and Albert, <unitdate type="inclusive">undated</unitdate>, <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1943">1943</unitdate></unittitle>
              </did>
            </c04>
            <c04 level="file">
              <did>
                <container type="box" label="Box">1</container>
                <unittitle>To Carol Kahn, <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1971/1981">1971-1981</unitdate></unittitle>
              </did>
            </c04>
            <c04 level="file">
              <did>
                <container type="box" label="Box">1</container>
                <unittitle>To and from Edgar regarding Journal of A Neurosurgeon, <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1971/1984">1971-1984</unitdate></unittitle>
              </did>
            </c04>
            <c04 level="file">
              <did>
                <container type="box" label="Box">1</container>
                <unittitle>Letters of condolence to Rose Kahn following Edgar's death, <unitdate type="inclusive">8/29/1985-10/24/1985</unitdate></unittitle>
              </did>
            </c04>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <container type="box" label="Box">1</container>
              <unittitle>U. S. Army and Red Cross documents, <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1940/1968">1940-1968</unitdate></unittitle>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Medical Career</unittitle>
            </did>
            <c04 level="file">
              <did>
                <container type="box" label="Box">1</container>
                <unittitle>Notes on general surgery, neurology, medicine and famous authors, <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1926">1926</unitdate></unittitle>
              </did>
            </c04>
            <c04 level="file">
              <did>
                <unittitle>Notes on surgical patients and procedures,</unittitle>
              </did>
              <c05 level="file">
                <did>
                  <container type="box" label="Box">1</container>
                  <unittitle>Journal, <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1930/1935">1930-1935</unitdate></unittitle>
                </did>
                <accessrestrict>
                  <p>[CR Restricted until <date type="restriction" normal="2035-07-01">July 1, 2035</date>; removed to vault]</p>
                </accessrestrict>
              </c05>
              <c05 level="file">
                <did>
                  <container type="box" label="Box">1</container>
                  <unittitle>Journal, <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1955">1955</unitdate></unittitle>
                </did>
                <accessrestrict>
                  <p>[CR Restricted until <date type="restriction" normal="2035-07-01">July 1, 2035</date>; removed to vault]</p>
                </accessrestrict>
              </c05>
            </c04>
            <c04 level="file">
              <did>
                <container type="box" label="Box">1</container>
                <unittitle>Letter citing qualifications for promotion to Professor of Surgery, undated, <unitdate type="inclusive">ca. 1949</unitdate></unittitle>
              </did>
            </c04>
            <c04 level="file">
              <did>
                <unittitle>Lectures by and about Edgar Kahn's work</unittitle>
              </did>
              <c05 level="file">
                <did>
                  <container type="box" label="Box">1</container>
                  <unittitle>Notes on career of Dr. Elizabeth Crosby, <unitdate type="inclusive">undated</unitdate></unittitle>
                </did>
              </c05>
              <c05 level="file">
                <did>
                  <container type="box" label="Box">1</container>
                  <unittitle>"Random Remarks on Surgery and Surgeons," <unitdate type="inclusive">undated</unitdate></unittitle>
                </did>
              </c05>
              <c05 level="file">
                <did>
                  <container type="box" label="Box">1</container>
                  <unittitle>Miscellaneous, <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1934/1972">1934-1972</unitdate></unittitle>
                </did>
              </c05>
            </c04>
            <c04 level="file">
              <did>
                <container type="box" label="Box">1</container>
                <unittitle>Edgar Kahn's Congress of Neurosurgery Pendant, <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1964">1964</unitdate></unittitle>
              </did>
            </c04>
            <c04 level="file">
              <did>
                <container type="box" label="Box">1</container>
                <unittitle>Neurosurgical Meeting Programs, 6/8/1934-11/8-9/1985</unittitle>
              </did>
            </c04>
            <c04 level="file">
              <did>
                <container type="box" label="Box">1</container>
                <unittitle>Head Protection Laboratory, <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1975/1981">1975-1981</unitdate></unittitle>
              </did>
            </c04>
            <c04 level="file">
              <did>
                <container type="box" label="Box">1</container>
                <unittitle>Neurosurgery journal articles by and about Edgar Kahn, <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1949/1984">1949-1984</unitdate></unittitle>
              </did>
            </c04>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Newspaper Articles, <unitdate type="inclusive">ca. 1921-1960s</unitdate></unittitle>
            </did>
            <c04 level="file">
              <did>
                <container type="box" label="Box">1</container>
                <unittitle>University of Michigan Hockey Team, <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1921">1921</unitdate></unittitle>
              </did>
            </c04>
            <c04 level="file">
              <did>
                <container type="box" label="Box">1</container>
                <unittitle>World War II, <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1939/1945">1939-1945</unitdate></unittitle>
              </did>
            </c04>
            <c04 level="file">
              <did>
                <container type="box" label="Box">1</container>
                <unittitle>Medical career, <unitdate type="inclusive">undated</unitdate>, <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1984">1984</unitdate></unittitle>
              </did>
            </c04>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <container type="box" label="Box">1</container>
              <unittitle>Writings by Edgar Kahn about Albert Kahn, <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1984">1984</unitdate>, <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1985">1985</unitdate></unittitle>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Miscellaneous Papers</unittitle>
            </did>
            <c04 level="file">
              <did>
                <container type="box" label="Box">1</container>
                <unittitle>Birth certificate, <unitdate type="inclusive">4/17/1900</unitdate></unittitle>
              </did>
            </c04>
            <c04 level="file">
              <did>
                <container type="box" label="Box">1</container>
                <unittitle>Phillips Academy (Andover) memorabilia and scrapbook, <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1917/1918">1917-1918</unitdate> </unittitle>
              </did>
              <odd>
                <p>(copies of scrapbook pages due to degradation of originals)</p>
              </odd>
            </c04>
            <c04 level="file">
              <did>
                <container type="box" label="Box">1</container>
                <unittitle>Phillips Academy (Andover) and University of Michigan diplomas, <unitdate type="inclusive">6/14/1918</unitdate>, <unitdate type="inclusive">6/16/1924</unitdate></unittitle>
              </did>
            </c04>
            <c04 level="file">
              <did>
                <container type="box" label="Box">1</container>
                <unittitle>Passports, <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1929/1933">1929-1933</unitdate>, <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1934/1938">1934-1938</unitdate></unittitle>
              </did>
            </c04>
            <c04 level="file">
              <did>
                <container type="box" label="Box">1</container>
                <unittitle>Guest Book, <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1950/1958">1950-1958</unitdate></unittitle>
              </did>
            </c04>
            <c04 level="file">
              <did>
                <container type="box" label="Box">1</container>
                <unittitle>Pencil drawings, <unitdate type="inclusive">undated</unitdate></unittitle>
              </did>
            </c04>
            <c04 level="file">
              <did>
                <container type="box" label="Box">1</container>
                <unittitle>Journal with handwritten jokes, <unitdate type="inclusive">undated</unitdate></unittitle>
              </did>
            </c04>
            <c04 level="file">
              <did>
                <container type="box" label="Box">1</container>
                <unittitle>Club rosters, <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1981/1985">1981-1985</unitdate></unittitle>
              </did>
            </c04>
            <c04 level="file">
              <did>
                <container type="box" label="Box">1</container>
                <unittitle>Plat map of J. D. Baldwin's Eastern Addition to the City of Ann Arbor, <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1866">1866</unitdate></unittitle>
              </did>
            </c04>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Photographs</unittitle>
            </did>
            <c04 level="file">
              <did>
                <container type="box" label="Box">1</container>
                <unittitle>Edgar Kahn, <unitdate type="inclusive">ca. 1904-1980</unitdate> </unittitle>
                <physdesc>
                  <extent>twenty 2-1/2x3-1/2 to 8x11-inch, black-and white prints and one 5x7-inch, color print</extent>
                </physdesc>
              </did>
            </c04>
            <c04 level="file">
              <did>
                <container type="box" label="Box">1</container>
                <unittitle>World War I, <unitdate type="inclusive">undated</unitdate> </unittitle>
                <physdesc>
                  <extent>one 2x3-inch and seven 3x4-inch, black-and-white prints</extent>
                </physdesc>
              </did>
            </c04>
            <c04 level="file">
              <did>
                <container type="box" label="Box">1</container>
                <unittitle>Medical career, <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1922/1984">1922-1984</unitdate> </unittitle>
                <physdesc>
                  <physfacet>thirty-one 2x3 to 9x13-inch, black-and-white prints and five 3-1/2x5-inch, color prints</physfacet>
                </physdesc>
              </did>
            </c04>
            <c04 level="file">
              <did>
                <container type="box" label="Box">1</container>
                <unittitle>Edgar with Diego Rivera, Frida Kahlo and Ernestine Kahn on his 32nd birthday, <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1932">1932</unitdate> </unittitle>
                <physdesc>
                  <physfacet>one 8x10-inch photocopy</physfacet>
                </physdesc>
              </did>
            </c04>
            <c04 level="file">
              <did>
                <container type="box" label="Box">1</container>
                <unittitle>Travels and friends, unidentified and <unitdate type="inclusive">undated</unitdate> </unittitle>
                <physdesc>
                  <extent>fifty-one 3x5 to 7x9-inch, black and white prints</extent>
                </physdesc>
              </did>
              <odd>
                <p>(two identified as Iran, 1934)</p>
              </odd>
            </c04>
            <c04 level="file">
              <did>
                <container type="box" label="Box">2</container>
                <unittitle>Edgar with Albert and Ernestine Kahn, <unitdate type="inclusive">ca. 1939</unitdate> </unittitle>
                <physdesc>
                  <extent>one 5x7-inch, black-and-white print</extent>
                </physdesc>
              </did>
            </c04>
            <c04 level="file">
              <did>
                <container type="box" label="Box">2</container>
                <unittitle>World War II, <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1939/1945">1939-1945</unitdate> </unittitle>
                <physdesc>
                  <extent>eight 2-1/2x4 to 7x10-inch, black-and-white prints</extent>
                </physdesc>
              </did>
            </c04>
            <c04 level="file">
              <did>
                <container type="box" label="Box">2</container>
                <unittitle>Trip to Bilbao, Spain, <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1940">1940</unitdate> </unittitle>
                <physdesc>
                  <extent>five 8x10-inch, black-and-white prints and one 4-1/2x6-inch, pencil caricature</extent>
                </physdesc>
              </did>
            </c04>
            <c04 level="file">
              <did>
                <container type="box" label="Box">2</container>
                <unittitle>Rose, Allen, Carol, Betsy and Barbara, <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1948">1948</unitdate>, <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1962">1962</unitdate>, <unitdate type="inclusive">undated</unitdate> </unittitle>
                <physdesc>
                  <extent>twenty-one 2x2 to 5x7-inch, black-and-white and color prints</extent>
                </physdesc>
              </did>
            </c04>
            <c04 level="file">
              <did>
                <container type="box" label="Box">2</container>
                <unittitle>Rose Herrmann Kahn (Dr. Rose Parker) at Mackinac Island, <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1948">1948</unitdate> </unittitle>
                <physdesc>
                  <extent>three 8x10-inch, black-and-white prints</extent>
                </physdesc>
              </did>
            </c04>
            <c04 level="file">
              <did>
                <container type="box" label="Box">2</container>
                <unittitle>Trip to Greece and Italy with Rose Kahn and Ruth and Edward Rothman, <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1961">1961</unitdate> </unittitle>
                <physdesc>
                  <physfacet>fifteen 3x4-1/2-inch, color prints</physfacet>
                </physdesc>
              </did>
            </c04>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Audio-Visual Materials</unittitle>
            </did>
            <c04 level="file">
              <did>
                <container type="box" label="Box">2</container>
                <unittitle>Carol Kahn's interview with Edgar Kahn, <unitdate type="inclusive">2/11/1978</unitdate> </unittitle>
                <physdesc>
                  <physfacet>reel-to-reel audio tape, two hours in length, and transcription</physfacet>
                </physdesc>
              </did>
            </c04>
            <c04 level="file">
              <did>
                <container type="box" label="Box">2</container>
                <unittitle>Lecture by Edgar Kahn to Cook County Graduate School of Medicine, "Philosophy of a Neurosurgeon," <unitdate type="inclusive">undated</unitdate> </unittitle>
                <physdesc>
                  <physfacet>audio-cassette</physfacet>
                </physdesc>
              </did>
            </c04>
            <c04 level="file">
              <did>
                <container type="box" label="Box">2</container>
                <unittitle>Edgar Kahn Memorial Service, <unitdate type="inclusive">9/3/1985</unitdate> </unittitle>
                <physdesc>
                  <physfacet>audio-cassette</physfacet>
                </physdesc>
              </did>
            </c04>
            <c04 level="file">
              <did>
                <container type="box" label="Box">2</container>
                <unittitle>Kahn Society Memorial Lecture by J. Talem, "Eddie Kahn," <unitdate type="inclusive">11/8/1985</unitdate> </unittitle>
                <physdesc>
                  <physfacet>audio-cassette</physfacet>
                </physdesc>
              </did>
            </c04>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <container type="box" label="Box">2</container>
              <unittitle>Obituary, <unitdate type="inclusive">9/1/1985</unitdate></unittitle>
            </did>
          </c03>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Rosalie Kahn Butzel</unittitle>
          </did>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <container type="box" label="Box">2</container>
              <unittitle>Obituary, <unitdate type="inclusive">10/4/1999</unitdate></unittitle>
            </did>
          </c03>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Carol Kahn</unittitle>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>The Carol Kahn sub-series includes a collection of newspaper articles, letters and photographs describing the efforts of a group of Ann Arbor citizens to "Save Old Main," The University of Michigan Hospital, which Albert Kahn designed and built in 1921 and in which her father practiced neurosurgery. Carol was active in this 1989 preservation campaign, which succeeded in saving the entry arch of her grandfather's historic hospital and in establishing the Albert Kahn Commemorative Art Project at the hospital.</p>
          </scopecontent>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <container type="box" label="Box">2 </container>
              <unittitle>"Saving Old Main" Campaign, <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1988/1989">1988-1989</unitdate></unittitle>
            </did>
            <c04 level="file">
              <did>
                <container type="box" label="Box">2 </container>
                <unittitle>"Old Main's Administrative Wing: A Proposal for Preservation" by Nicholas H. Steneck, <unitdate type="inclusive">2/1988</unitdate></unittitle>
              </did>
            </c04>
            <c04 level="file">
              <did>
                <container type="box" label="Box">2 </container>
                <unittitle>Newspaper articles, <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1989">1989</unitdate></unittitle>
              </did>
            </c04>
            <c04 level="file">
              <did>
                <container type="box" label="Box">2 </container>
                <unittitle>Correspondence, <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1989">1989</unitdate></unittitle>
              </did>
            </c04>
            <c04 level="file">
              <did>
                <container type="box" label="Box">2 </container>
                <unittitle>Photographs, <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1920">1920</unitdate>, <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1989">1989</unitdate> </unittitle>
                <physdesc>
                  <extent>one 8-1/2x11-inch copy print and 37 35 mm negatives</extent>
                </physdesc>
              </did>
            </c04>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <container type="box" label="Box">2 </container>
              <unittitle>Albert Kahn Commemorative Art Project, University Hospital, <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1990/1991">1990-1991</unitdate></unittitle>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <container type="box" label="Box">2 </container>
              <unittitle>Renaming of the New Center Building, "The Albert Kahn Building," <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1988">1988</unitdate></unittitle>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <container type="box" label="Box">2 </container>
              <unittitle>Correspondence, <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1990/1998">1990-1998</unitdate></unittitle>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <container type="box" label="Box">2 </container>
              <unittitle>Newspaper article, <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1999">1999</unitdate></unittitle>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <container type="box" label="Box">2 </container>
              <unittitle>Photographs of Carol Kahn and Dennis Kittel family, canoeing in Algonquin Park, Ontario, <unitdate type="inclusive">ca. 1989</unitdate> </unittitle>
              <physdesc>
                <extent>eighteen 35 mm. negatives</extent>
              </physdesc>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="item">
            <did>
              <container type="box" label="Box">2 </container>
              <unittitle>Architectural publication and photograph from family library</unittitle>
            </did>
            <c04 level="file">
              <did>
                <container type="box" label="Box">2 </container>
                <unittitle>Hahner-Murdock, Christine.<title render="italic">Images in Stone: Detroit -- The First 300 Years</title>. Detroit: Christine Hahner-Murdock, <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="2005">2005</unitdate></unittitle>
              </did>
            </c04>
            <c04 level="file">
              <did>
                <container type="box" label="Box">2 </container>
                <unittitle>Ford Motor Company Rotunda Building, Dearborn, by Paul W. Gilbert, <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1960">1960</unitdate></unittitle>
              </did>
            </c04>
          </c03>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Kahn Family Papers, William R. Brashear and Ruth Brashear Carrigan, collectors</unittitle>
        </did>
        <scopecontent>
          <p>The William R. Brashear and Ruth Brashear Carrigan, collectors series is comprised of files named for the family members with papers in the collection, including Albert Kahn, Ernestine Krolik Kahn, Ruth Kahn Rothman, Edward E. Rothman, Mrs. Eli Rothman, Lydia Kahn Winston Malbin, Rosalie Kahn Butzel, Josephine Rothman Treutner, Lydia Rothman Brashear, William R. Brashear, Ruth Brashear Carrigan, Lydia Brashear Tiede, and Elizabeth (Betsy) Kahn Lehndorff.</p>
          <p>Of particular interest within the Ruth Kahn Rothman file are twelve folders of letters written by Edward E. Rothman, while she was a student at Emma Willard School in 1922, and later, during his service in Northern Africa and France in World War II. Also of significance are letters from her parents, written between 1923 and 1929, which give insight into Albert's and Ernestine's relationship with their daughter. Newspaper articles about her marriage and her community service over many years further enrich the perspective on Ruth's life.</p>
          <p>The Edward E. Rothman file includes his official Army papers and newspaper articles about his assignments abroad during World War II. Biographical materials in the form of articles, letters and press releases illuminate the married lives of Ruth and Edward, as well as his professional career and philanthropic activities with Michigan State University and the Detroit Institute of Arts Founders' Society. Photographs of the Kahn and Rothman families are also of interest, including a set of slides (with viewer), taken in 1956, with a popular, stereoscopic camera of the day.</p>
          <p>Miscellaneous articles about Kahn's daughters, Rosalie Butzel and Lydia Winston Malbin, and granddaughters, Josephine Rothman Treutner, Lydia Rothman Brashear and Elizabeth Kahn Lehndorff, further enrich the intergenerational family picture. The files of the two Rothman daughters, Jospehine and Lydia, contain their wedding albums and more stereoscopic slides of these events, from 1956 and 1961. Because Lydia was Mr. Brashear's wife, his collection contains a few letters from her grandfather, Albert Kahn, and documents pertaining to her early equestrian activities.</p>
          <p>Included in the William R. Brashear file is a copy of a book which he wrote in 1977, entitled, <title render="italic">The Gorgon's Head</title> , and his important volume, <title render="italic">Albert Kahn and His Family in Peace and War</title> , which was published by the Bentley Historical Library in 2006. Mr. Brashear was a literature scholar, with degrees from the University of Michigan and Princeton University. He also practiced law in Livonia, Michigan. He preserved the collection of family materials which his wife Lydia Rothman Brashear had amassed from her grandparents, mother and father and used them as primary source material in the writing of his book on Albert Kahn. The original letters and photographs are included in the Albert and Ernestine Kahn, Ruth Kahn Rothman, Edward E. Rothman and Lydia Rothman Brashear file of his collection here. He donated these documents to the Bentley Historical Library after the completion of his book and with the help of his daughter Ruth Brashear Carrigan, after his death in 2014. Copies of the letters and photographs which were used in his book are included within the William Brashear file.</p>
        </scopecontent>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Albert Kahn</unittitle>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>The Albert Kahn sub-series contains letters from his wife and daughter Lydia, while traveling aboard the ship, "Mauretania," in 1923, as well as his obituary and documents related to the celebration of his enormous legacy, after his death. Obituaries and newspaper articles in the Ernestine Krolik Kahn sub-series describe some of her social and community involvements.</p>
          </scopecontent>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <container type="box" label="Box">2</container>
              <unittitle>Letters from Ernestine and Lydia Kahn, written aboard the "Mauretania," <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1923">1923</unitdate></unittitle>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <container type="box" label="Box">2</container>
              <unittitle>Obituaries, <unitdate type="inclusive">12/9/1942</unitdate></unittitle>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <container type="box" label="Box">2</container>
              <unittitle>Inventory of all Albert Kahn Associates publicity, <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1939/1945">1939-1945</unitdate></unittitle>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <container type="box" label="Box">2</container>
              <unittitle>Donation of Albert Kahn drawings to U-M, <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1969">1969</unitdate></unittitle>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <container type="box" label="Box">2</container>
              <unittitle>75th Anniversary of Albert Kahn Associates, Inc., Architects &amp; Engineers, <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1970">1970</unitdate></unittitle>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <container type="box" label="Box">2</container>
              <unittitle>Detroit Institute of Arts "Legacy of Albert Kahn" Exhibit, <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1970">1970</unitdate></unittitle>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <container type="box" label="Box">2</container>
              <unittitle>Re-Naming and dedication of Albert Kahn Building, <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1988">1988</unitdate></unittitle>
            </did>
          </c03>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Ernestine Krolik Kahn</unittitle>
          </did>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <container type="box" label="Box">2</container>
              <unittitle>Newspaper articles, <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1932/1937">1932-1937</unitdate></unittitle>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <container type="box" label="Box">2</container>
              <unittitle>Obituaries, <unitdate type="inclusive">12/7/1957</unitdate></unittitle>
            </did>
          </c03>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Ruth Kahn Rothman</unittitle>
          </did>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <container type="box" label="Box">2</container>
              <unittitle>Newspaper article, <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1918">1918</unitdate></unittitle>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <container type="box" label="Box">2</container>
              <unittitle>Letters from Albert and Ernestine Kahn, <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1923/1929">1923-1929</unitdate></unittitle>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <container type="box" label="Box">2</container>
              <unittitle>Letters received from Edward E. Rothman, <unitdate type="inclusive">May 1922-1924</unitdate>, <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1929">1929</unitdate>, <unitdate type="inclusive">undated</unitdate> </unittitle>
              <physdesc>
                <extent>12 folders</extent>
              </physdesc>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <container type="box" label="Box">2</container>
              <unittitle>Scrapbook/Photograph Album, Emma Willard School, Troy, New York, <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1923">1923</unitdate></unittitle>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <container type="box" label="Box">2</container>
              <unittitle>Diary and photograph album, Florence, Italy, <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1926">1926</unitdate></unittitle>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Newspaper articles</unittitle>
            </did>
            <c04 level="file">
              <did>
                <container type="box" label="Box">2</container>
                <unittitle>Engagement, marriage and parenthood, <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1929/1933">1929-1933</unitdate></unittitle>
              </did>
            </c04>
            <c04 level="file">
              <did>
                <container type="box" label="Box">2</container>
                <unittitle>Community activities, <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1931/1961">1931-1961</unitdate></unittitle>
              </did>
            </c04>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <container type="box" label="Box">2</container>
              <unittitle>Letters of condolence from Albert Kahn and others, <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1937">1937</unitdate></unittitle>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <container type="box" label="Box">2</container>
              <unittitle>Letters to Edward E. Rothman, <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1942/1943">1942-1943</unitdate></unittitle>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <container type="box" label="Box">2</container>
              <unittitle>Introduction of Lenore Romney, <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1963">1963</unitdate></unittitle>
            </did>
          </c03>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="subseries">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Edward E. Rothman</unittitle>
          </did>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <container type="box" label="Box">3</container>
              <unittitle>Confirmation service program, Temple Beth El, <unitdate type="inclusive">6/11/1913</unitdate></unittitle>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <container type="box" label="Box">3</container>
              <unittitle>U. S. Army Air Force orders and leave records, <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1942/1947">1942-1947</unitdate></unittitle>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <container type="box" label="Box">3</container>
              <unittitle>U. S. Army Air Force financial, insurance and miscellaneous records, <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1942/1945">1942-1945</unitdate></unittitle>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <container type="box" label="Box">3</container>
              <unittitle>Allied Forces messages from Generals H. R. Alexander, B. L. Montgomery and Dwight Eisenhower, <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1942/1943">1942-1943</unitdate></unittitle>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <container type="box" label="Box">3</container>
              <unittitle>U. S. Army certificates, awards and wartime newspaper articles, <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1917/1947">1917-1947</unitdate></unittitle>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <container type="box" label="Box">3</container>
              <unittitle>Wartime letters to Albert Kahn, Ernestine Kahn and Ruth Rothman, <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1943/1944">1943-1944</unitdate></unittitle>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <container type="box" label="Box">3</container>
              <unittitle>Business career, <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1927/1965">1927-1965</unitdate></unittitle>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <container type="box" label="Box">3</container>
              <unittitle>Detroit Institute of Art Founders' Society service, <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1953/1973">1953-1973</unitdate></unittitle>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <container type="box" label="Box">3</container>
              <unittitle>Michigan State University service and awards, <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1971/1982">1971-1982</unitdate></unittitle>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <container type="box" label="Box">3</container>
              <unittitle>Philanthropy correspondence, <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1966/1974">1966-1974</unitdate></unittitle>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <container type="box" label="Box">3</container>
              <unittitle>Correspondence with family, friends and colleagues, <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1959/1974">1959-1974</unitdate></unittitle>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <unittitle>Photographs</unittitle>
            </did>
            <c04 level="file">
              <did>
                <container type="box" label="Box">3</container>
                <unittitle>Kahn and Rothman families, late 19th century to <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1972">1972</unitdate> </unittitle>
                <physdesc>
                  <extent>eleven black-and-white and color images of various sizes, and one slide</extent>
                </physdesc>
              </did>
            </c04>
            <c04 level="file">
              <did>
                <container type="box" label="Box">3</container>
                <unittitle>Rothman family, <unitdate type="inclusive">undated</unitdate> </unittitle>
                <physdesc>
                  <physfacet>five 2-1/2x4-1/2-inch and forty-six 1-1/2x1-1/2-inch, black-and-white prints and negatives</physfacet>
                </physdesc>
              </did>
            </c04>
            <c04 level="file">
              <did>
                <container type="box" label="Box">3</container>
                <unittitle>Family and friends, <unitdate type="inclusive">July 1956</unitdate> </unittitle>
                <physdesc>
                  <physfacet>twenty-six stereoscopic slides, with viewer at back of box</physfacet>
                </physdesc>
              </did>
            </c04>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <container type="box" label="Box">3</container>
              <unittitle>Curriculum Vitae and obituary, <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1974">1974</unitdate></unittitle>
            </did>
          </c03>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Mrs. Eli Rothman</unittitle>
          </did>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <container type="box" label="Box">3</container>
              <unittitle>Letter to the Editor, Detroit News, <unitdate type="inclusive">ca. 1915</unitdate></unittitle>
            </did>
          </c03>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Lydia Kahn Winston Malbin</unittitle>
          </did>
          <c03 level="item">
            <did>
              <container type="box" label="Box">3</container>
              <unittitle>Newspaper Article, <unitdate type="inclusive">10/6/1974</unitdate></unittitle>
            </did>
          </c03>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Rosalie Kahn Butzel</unittitle>
          </did>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <container type="box" label="Box">3</container>
              <unittitle>Letter to the Editor, <unitdate type="inclusive">undated</unitdate></unittitle>
            </did>
          </c03>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Josephine Rothman Treutner</unittitle>
          </did>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <container type="box" label="Box">3</container>
              <unittitle>Newspaper articles, <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1943/1947">1943-1947</unitdate></unittitle>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <container type="box" label="Box">3</container>
              <unittitle>Wedding photographs album, <unitdate type="inclusive">6/30/1956</unitdate></unittitle>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <container type="box" label="Box">3</container>
              <unittitle>Wedding photographs, <unitdate type="inclusive">6/30/1956</unitdate> </unittitle>
              <physdesc>
                <physfacet>twenty-seven stereoscopic slides, with viewer at back of box</physfacet>
              </physdesc>
            </did>
          </c03>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Lydia Rothman Brashear</unittitle>
          </did>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <container type="box" label="Box">3</container>
              <unittitle>Letters from Albert Kahn, <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1936">1936</unitdate>, <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1941">1941</unitdate></unittitle>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <container type="box" label="Box">3</container>
              <unittitle>Letters to Edward Rothman, <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1943/1944">1943-1944</unitdate></unittitle>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <container type="box" label="Box">3</container>
              <unittitle>Horseback-riding competitions. <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1944">1944</unitdate></unittitle>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <container type="box" label="Box">3</container>
              <unittitle>Poster photo from Grosse Pointe Hunt Club Horse Show, <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1947">1947</unitdate></unittitle>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <container type="box" label="Box">4</container>
              <unittitle>Newspaper article, <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1949">1949</unitdate></unittitle>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <container type="box" label="Box">4</container>
              <unittitle>Graduation and marriage, <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1956">1956</unitdate>, <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1961">1961</unitdate></unittitle>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <container type="box" label="Box">4</container>
              <unittitle>Wedding photographs album, <unitdate type="inclusive">1/14/1961</unitdate></unittitle>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <container type="box" label="Box">4</container>
              <unittitle>Wedding photographs, <unitdate type="inclusive">1/14/1961</unitdate> </unittitle>
              <physdesc>
                <physfacet>sixty-three stereoscopic slides, with viewer at back of Box 3</physfacet>
              </physdesc>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <container type="box" label="Box">4</container>
              <unittitle>Correspondence, <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1968/1980">1968-1980</unitdate></unittitle>
            </did>
          </c03>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>William R. Brashear</unittitle>
          </did>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <container type="box" label="Box">4</container>
              <unittitle><title render="italic">The Gorgon's Head</title>, Athens: The University of Georgia Press, <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1977">1977</unitdate></unittitle>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <container type="box" label="Box">4</container>
              <unittitle><title render="italic">Albert Kahn and His Family in Peace and War,</title> Ann Arbor: Bentley Historical Library, <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="2006">2006</unitdate></unittitle>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <container type="box" label="Box">4</container>
              <unittitle>
                <title render="italic">Albert Kahn and His Family in Peace and War,</title>
                <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="2006">2006</unitdate>
              </unittitle>
              <physdesc>
                <physfacet>manuscript copy</physfacet>
              </physdesc>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <container type="box" label="Box">4</container>
              <unittitle>Letters from Albert, Ernestine, Lydia and Ruth Kahn and Edward Rothman to family members, <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1923/1944">1923-1944</unitdate> </unittitle>
              <physdesc>
                <physfacet>transcriptions and copies of originals, used by William Brashear inAlbert Kahn and His Family in Peace and War</physfacet>
              </physdesc>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <container type="box" label="Box">4</container>
              <unittitle>Photographs of Albert, Ernestine and Edgar Khan, Ruth and Edward Rothman, other family members, Henry Joy, William Clements, Eliel Saarinen, Henry Ford and Glenn Martin, and drawings of Kahn buildings, <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1900/1975">1900-1975</unitdate> </unittitle>
              <physdesc>
                <physfacet>copies of originals, used by William Brashear in Albert Kahn and His Family in Peace and War</physfacet>
              </physdesc>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <container type="box" label="Box">4</container>
              <unittitle>Curriculum Vitae</unittitle>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <container type="box" label="Box">4</container>
              <unittitle>Obituary and Memorial Service program, <unitdate type="inclusive">5/25/2014</unitdate></unittitle>
            </did>
          </c03>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Ruth Brashear Carrigan</unittitle>
          </did>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <container type="box" label="Box">4</container>
              <unittitle>Letter to Edward Rothman, <unitdate type="inclusive">undated</unitdate></unittitle>
            </did>
          </c03>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Lydia Brashear Tiede</unittitle>
          </did>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <container type="box" label="Box">4</container>
              <unittitle>Letters to and from Edward Rothman, <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="1965">1965</unitdate></unittitle>
            </did>
          </c03>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Elizabeth (Betsy) Kahn (Lehndorff)</unittitle>
          </did>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <container type="box" label="Box">4</container>
              <unittitle>Newspaper Article, <unitdate type="inclusive">8/13/1969</unitdate></unittitle>
            </did>
          </c03>
        </c02>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Miscellaneous</unittitle>
          </did>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <container type="box" label="Box">4</container>
              <unittitle>Newspaper article about Eliel Saarinen, <unitdate type="inclusive">undated</unitdate></unittitle>
            </did>
          </c03>
        </c02>
      </c01>
      <c01 level="series">
        <did>
          <unittitle>Kahn Family Papers, Elizabeth (Betsy) Kahn Lehndorff, collector</unittitle>
        </did>
        <c02 level="file">
          <did>
            <unittitle>Elizabeth (Betsy) Kahn Lehndorff</unittitle>
          </did>
          <scopecontent>
            <p>The series, Kahn Family Papers, Elizabeth (Betsy) Kahn Lehndorff, collector, is named for the granddaughter of Albert and Ernestine Kahn and daughter of Edgar A. Kahn, who has donated materials related to her own career, as a journalist and jewelry artist. It is expected that the third and fourth generations of Kahns will continue to keep the record of this accomplished family alive through ongoing donations of materials.</p>
          </scopecontent>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <container type="box" label="Box">4 </container>
              <unittitle>"Rocky Mountain News" articles, <unitdate type="inclusive" normal="2001/2007">2001-2007</unitdate></unittitle>
            </did>
          </c03>
          <c03 level="file">
            <did>
              <container type="box" label="Box">4 </container>
              <unittitle>Jewelry Exhibit, University of Michigan Health System, <unitdate type="inclusive">12/15/2014-2/1/2015</unitdate></unittitle>
            </did>
          </c03>
        </c02>
      </c01>
    </dsc>
    <descgrp type="add">
      <relatedmaterial>
        <head>Related Material</head>
        <p><title show="replace" actuate="onrequest" href="http://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/f/findaid/findaid-idx?c=bhlead;idno=umich-bhl-0420">The Albert Kahn Papers</title>, donated by his firm Albert Kahn Associates, Inc. in 2003, include 13 linear feet of correspondence, transcripts of speeches, newspaper articles and construction photographs of many of Kahn's most significant buildings. In addition, almost 10,000 original, ink-on-linen construction drawings of 200 of his industrial, commercial, institutional and residential projects are housed in flat-file drawers. The narrative and visual documents in this large collection give researchers the opportunity to study many aspects of the master architect's career and life, from his personal views on industrial architecture contained in his speeches, to the drawings which preserve his iconic buildings for posterity on paper.</p>
      </relatedmaterial>
    </descgrp>
  </archdesc>
</ead>
